<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MM</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/feeds/mobile.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://michaelmartinez.in/</id><updated>2011-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>UKDroidCon 2011</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/ukdroidcon-2011.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-08-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaelmartinez.in,2011-08-31:ukdroidcon-2011.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check this OUT!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This &lt;a href="http://uk.droidcon.com/"&gt;droidcon event&lt;/a&gt; looks AWESOME. Today is the last day to
register at the early bird pricing, you know quids and all that. If you
live in the UK, you owe it to yourself to get there and get your learn
on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at this amazing line up:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DAY ONE - BARCAMP/DEMOCAMP&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day will start at 9AM to meet up and vote for the Barcamp
presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 10:30 ish the Barcamp will be in full swing with 10s of presentation
to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 17:00 we'll get started for the Democamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by 19:00 we should all be gathering for Beer&amp;amp;Pizzacamp!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DAY TWO - CONFERENCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day will start around 9AM and finish by 6PM. Then you can
join one of the many post-conference drinks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wireframing Like A Pro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greg Taylor - Tigerspike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greg Taylor will talk about Wireframing like a pro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concurrency And Multi-Core &amp;amp; Honeycomb&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al Sutton - Funky Android&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al will be talking about the mayhem of Multi-core. He'll teach you why
more cores can be good for an application and show you when, and how,
you can make use of any extra cores which might be available on the
device your application runs on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android@Home, Bluetooth @ Android, Wireless M2M&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harald Naumann&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harald Naumann will talk about Android@Home, Bluetooth @ Android and
Wireless M2M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaming and Bluevia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yosi Taguri - Bluevia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yosi Taguri will talk about Gaming and Bluevia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mobile Enterprise Security And The Need For Mobile Device Management&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Goode&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan will talk about the use of mobile phones in the enterprise and
share his experience of the Mobile Device Management market.
Organisations are being challenged by employees bringing in their own
mobile devices and expecting to access corporate networks and store
corporate information. Alan will discuss some of the security challenges
that this ‘Consumerisation’ trend is creating and how organisations are
meeting this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Hyndman - Google&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Hyndmann will talk about Google Fragments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operator APIs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Parton - O2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Parton will talk about Operator API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Intents - Historify And Other Aggregating Apps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friedger Müffke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friedger Müffke will talk about Historify And Other Aggregating
Applications (Google Summer Of Code Project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kick-starting Android Application Development&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthias Kaeppler - Qype&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthias will talk about kick-starting Android Application Development:
"Due to its basis in Java, the Android SDK is a simple way to get
started with app development, even for those developers not coming from
a mobile background. Still, the Android framework lacks standard,
re-usable solutions to many recurring tasks, making it more difficult
than necessary to get an application off the ground quickly. Thanks to
the amazing Android development community, we have plenty of utility
libraries today that patch these holes in the Android framework. In this
talk I will present a selection of these freely available libraries,
which will help kick-start app development, by managing your objects and
builds, and by offering ready-to-use solutions for the most common
issues."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Geeksphone Story&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Javier Agüera - Geeksphone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Javier Agüera will talk about the Geeksphone story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android Gaming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mustafa Isik - CodeSurgeon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mustafa Isik will talk about Android Gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D Advertising&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terence Eden - Inmobi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terence will talk about the Reality of Mobile Advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test-Driving Android Applications with Roboelectric&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph Moore - Pivotal Labs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph will talk about why and how Robolectric was built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reforming Addicts Or iOS To Android Made Easy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kieran Gutteridge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kieran will talk about reforming addicts or iOS to Android made easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UI For Tablet &amp;amp; Phone and TV&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Butcher - Google&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Butcher will talk about UI For Tablet &amp;amp; Phone and TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android's Message-Driven Architecture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carl Gustaf Harroch - Novoda&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Droidcon London 2011, Carl-Gustaf Harroch will explain Android's
Message-driven Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps to Best Beta Releases&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon Vlachoyiannis - Bugsense&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jon Vlachoyiannis will talk about testing, specifically Steps to Best
Beta Releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motion Recognition with Android Devices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabor Paller - Sfonge Ltd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A built-in accelerometer is an almost obligatory feature of Android
devices. This sensor enables the auto-rotation feature and is used e.g.
in game applications for tilt-controlling the action. This presentation
discusses the usage of accelerometer for detecting dynamic motion
patterns. Shake or walk detection are very common use cases but exotic
features like dance detection can also improve the usability of a
specific application significantly. Android does not have platform-level
motion recognizer module therefore developers need to be aware, how to
detect motion patterns in the accelerometer's sample stream. We will
examine the most frequently used motion detection methods. The effect on
battery consumption will also be presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Massively Scalable c2dm with QoS and SLAs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dylan Boyd - Urban Air Ship&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dylan Boyd will talk about Push notifications, specifically massively
scalable c2dm with QoS and SLAs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traceview and MAT for Fun and Profit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Murphy - CommonsWare&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Murphy will talk about Traceview and MAT for Fun and Profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How To Run A Private Beta On The Android Market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thai Tran - Lightbox&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thai will talk about How To Run A Private Beta On The Android Market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making Sense of In-App Billing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hermes Pique Robot Media&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android In-App Billing is not for the faint of heart! Hermes Pique will
introduce the core concepts behind the Android Market's Billing Service,
and get you up and running with a working example using his open-source
Android Billing Library.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Tablet UI/UX Design Considerations</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/tablet-uiux-design-considerations.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaelmartinez.in,2011-05-13:tablet-uiux-design-considerations.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;User Interface / User Experience design is obviously a major aspect of
app design/development and one worthy, in my opinion, of considerable
pontification. I've watched several videos regarding UI / NUI design
and skimmed a few books. This aspect of development is really
interesting to me and I plan on writing about it a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like the video here (click the picture above to play embedded
version). Bill Van Hecke is the lead UI/UX designer for the Omni group
and narrates the entire video. As I madly (digitally) scribbled notes (I
love Evernote)... I thought I'd share.  Full disclosure: Yes, the video
is for iPad... Android is obviously my platform of choice, but I
recognize a good design when I see it. We can learn a lot from the iOS
ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​1. Brutally Massacre Features - is the app still useful to the average
user without this feature? If not, kill it dead.. at least initially.
Simplify your UI as it helps make it more intuitive. It also helps to
keep the project manageable from a development point of view. As with
most things in life; the KISS principle applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​2. The Android tablet is not a giant phone - I'm super guilty of this
as of this writing and I intend on rectifying this post-haste. Don't
simply reuse your main layouts for the large and extra-large resource
layout files. Not only is it super lazy design, its a total waste of
space. Furthermore, you are missing an opportunity to enhance your UX,
thus making your brand and app more desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​3. Adding design "space filler" isn't good practice - Now that you have
more space, adding elements and widgets to fill whitespace isn't good
design. You don't want a NASA Space shuttle cockpit. You need to think
about; control occlusion, accuracy, distractions and context. Hide
buttons/menus behind logically groups menu and button items. Only
display relevant controls for the context of the object in focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​4. Progressive disclosure - Universal Principles of Design. If you need
three columns stuffed with controls; you are probably making your user
think way too much, increasing the chance of distraction and not using
the power of contextual menus/buttons. Taps are cheap from a cognitive
load perspective, so make more objects "tap-able" and provide useful
contextual actions based on those taps. The rarer something is, the more
acceptable it is to bury the item deeper in lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​5. Taps are especially cheap in the Steering wheel zone - The 90 or so
pixels going down the side of the app are super easy for users to reach
and tap while holding the tablet with two hands. Try to implement the
most actionable / relevant UI elements in this zone. The "middle" of the
app is a great place to display the users content. Be cognizant of
control occlusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​6. Think about your user eating a sandwich while using your app - I
think this is pretty self explanatory. Gestures are really neat and fun
when used in the right context. However, if your user constantly has to
maneuver the tablet or reposition themselves to use the app, you are
making them think too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​7. Tap, drag/swipe, touch &amp;amp; hold, double tap, pinch / un-pinch, rotate
- These are iOS's gestures. Like it or not my fellow Android-ians... the
Apple Marketing machine has cleverly trained future tablet users while
marketing their wares. They show these "basic" gestures in commercials
and elsewhere and research has shown these to be easily performed with
one hand. Other gestures can be included for "power-users" but don't
make them required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​8. You have approximately 250ms to show users that a command was
understood before they become confused, angry, anxious or other
emotional state that is undesirable. When a user interacts with the app,
it should respond with "something" be that a glowing, changing of state,
movement, etc. Let your users know that the action they just performed
is valid, even if it wasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​9. Forgiveness - Enable and empower users to explore and exercise
control over the app. Help them feel adventurous. Don't make them afraid
to explore for fear of breaking or ruin something. Playful | fearless, a
big part of the reason why children are better with new technology than
adults. They are AWESOME at failing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​10. Modality - Lots of basic gestures mean the exact same thing. For
example, the drag can be panning, moving an object, selecting multiple
objects and the list goes on. Setting explicit modes of operations
separates concerns and helps to clearly define how the gesture will
behave in mode. Usability testing becomes very important here. this can
be complicated for the developer and SHOULD make it easier for the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​11. Organize the app by meaning, not based on opinion - Your work-flow
may radically differ from your users work-flow. Embrace this, as I
really think this makes designing and implementing the app better for
the user and easier for the developer. DO think about how users will use
the app. DON'T try to predict and code to those assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Engineer Toolkit is publishing very soon!</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/engineer-toolkit-is-publishing-very-soon.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaelmartinez.in,2011-01-03:engineer-toolkit-is-publishing-very-soon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;95% of the Engineer Toolkit app is done. Stay tuned for more updates and
a dedicated page with lots-of-info!!!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Android Development</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/android-development.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-10-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaelmartinez.in,2010-10-25:android-development.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just completed started my first Android app. It works... and its damn
cool to see something you built on &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; phone. That said, there is
still a &lt;em&gt;TON&lt;/em&gt; of work to do. I hope that I'm not served with a &lt;a href="http://www.marketwatch.com/story/oracle-sues-google-for-patent-infringement-2010-08-12?dist=beforebell"&gt;cease
and desist&lt;/a&gt; order, as Oracle is suing Google for patent infringements
relating to Android development. Although, I once read if you're not
getting in trouble you're not trying hard enough... perhaps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the app, its a fire department related app and the only
competition retails his app at \$2.99. I've been thinking all along that
I will release free apps as long as I have a decent job and my family is
not wanting for anything. I believe in karma and as such,
I definitely don't want to be greedy (especially as so many people are
struggling to make ends meet in the current economic environment).  Not
to say this app cures cancer or something, but I imagine the other
developer may not like a free app similar to his... I don't know
anything about developer decorum in such circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll have more very soon... STAY TUNED!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Android Super Computer App</title><link href="http://michaelmartinez.in/android-super-computer-app.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Michael</name></author><id>tag:michaelmartinez.in,2010-09-08:android-super-computer-app.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Did you ever wish you had a super computer in your pocket? You know for
those debates at the firehouse; "Dude, I guarantee the human genome is
completely indexable with the touch of a button, guarantee!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the geniuses at MIT, you could potentially deliver on such a
promise. The &lt;a href="http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/2010/supercomputer-smart-phones-0901.html"&gt;rbAPPmit&lt;/a&gt; has serious muscle behind the funny little
green fella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&gt; The new software works in cases where the general form of a problem is
&gt; known in advance, but not the particulars. For instance, says Phuong
&gt; Huynh, a postdoc who worked on the project, a computer simulation of
&gt; fluid flow around an obstacle in a pipe could depend on a single
&gt; parameter: the radius of the obstacle. But for a given value of the
&gt; parameter, calculating the fluid flow could take an hour on a
&gt; supercomputer with 500 processing units. The researchers’ new software
&gt; can provide a very good approximation of the same calculation in a
&gt; matter of seconds."

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rather complex video explaining some functionality: &lt;a href="http://augustine.mit.edu/methodology/video_clips/rbAPPmit_Feb11_2010_demo3.wmv"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>